in this video you will learn how to use
the bredon litzenberger formula to
derive the risk neutral probability
density functions from option prices
this can be extremely useful because
actual computing of option prices can be
a time and computationally intensive
task especially when there you have
something that you're trying to do very
complex dynamics of and when there is
very high dimensionality the beauty of
the breeden leitzenberger formula is
that we can actually just compute this
complicated derivatives once at
different strikes for a particular tower
so time to maturity and we can get this
risk neutral probability distribution
function and be able to calculate a
whole bunch of complex derivatives
extremely simply and quickly so once
we've got a discrete pdf what we're
going to do is we're going to actually
use
linear regression to be able to smooth
out this function then we're going to
use a cumulative we're going to create
the cumulative density function and then
we're going to be able to price all
sorts of complex derivatives easily
using this risk neutral distribution
that we've defined for a particular time
first off what is it well the feynman
knack analysis enables us to define the
risk neutral probability in which we can
price options so we're going to let uh
this function in terms of the risk
neutral probability measure q
of st denote the terminal risk neutral
so the q under the q measure probability
at time t and we're going to let this f
risk neutral probability q
denote the cumulative probability
distribution function so a european call
option at time little t expiring at big
t with strike k
is priced
as follows so here we're using tower to
represent that time to maturity
so here we've got our call price in
terms of k and tau and we've got the
risk neutral discounted expectation of
our payoff so here we can expand that
using the indicator function and we can
get that this discounted integral
between k and infinity
of st minus k times by the probability
distribution function this risk neutral
density function in terms of our risk
neutral measure so how can we actually
calculate directly from this formula
well we're going to get into that so now
that we have this formula
in terms of
k and tau
in the case where the risk neutral
density function is log normal density
and volatility is constant with respect
to k then this yields the black shoals
formula so under the basic no arbitrage
restrictions we can consider more
general densities than just this log
normal distribution of the underlying so
here we can use the breeden
litzenberger
formula from 1978 to show that the first
derivative is a function of the
cumulative distribution function
so here what we mean is if we take the
first derivative with respect to k
of this
integral here then we actually get minus
this exponential discount factor
times by 1 minus the cumulative density
function so the second derivative then
extracts the pdf so if you then take the
second derivative with respect to the
strike centered around k equals st then
what you get is the discount factor
multiplied by this wrist neutral pdf now
thanks to bruce uh mizerak in chapter 35
for putting a lot of this information
together in a very easy format to
understand i recommend going to this
link
link in the description and he's written
a whole bunch of things on estimating
applied probabilities from options
prices and underlying great resource
there
so
for python let's go and see how we can
actually apply this bit to actually get
this risk neutral distribution so here
we're going to have numpy we've got
scipy pandas
scipy we need to import stats explicitly
and then we're going to use matplotlib
now let's look at what we're going to be
pricing today we've got a european call
option with stochastic volatility
stochastic volatility is going to be
under the hester model so our wrist
neutral dynamics for the underlying
process here we've got our drift and our
diffusion term that we're used to seeing
now here the variance this uh square
root variance process is going to be
modeled with this sde which of course
you'll recognize from the hester model
and we have previous videos on the
dynamics of this
now here we've got a correlation p
just that is the correlation between
these two winer processes
between the variance process and then
the stock
underlying process
so let's initialize our parameters here
we've got a stock price of 100
strike of 150 tower is one and then an
annual risk free rate of six percent
heston dependent models who cares you
could take this from market data we've
done that before i'm using machine
learning techniques under the risk
neutral measure to be able to find what
these factors are go and take a look at
that video if you're interested in that
process here i'm just defining kappa is
three which is the rate of mean
reversion we've got theta which is the
long term variance so
i've just got
this
volatilities of 20
long term and then we've got the initial
volatility which is 20
and again variance so we're squaring
these numbers and here we've got rho
which is the correlation between returns
and variances i wanted a really skewed
uh wrist initial distribution i don't
want a log normal distribution so i've
made this positive 0.98 so that'll show
an interesting effect on our risk
neutral distribution
and here we've got sigma which is the
volatility of volatility
which is
this factor here so here i've called
that 20
now the risk premium of variance i'm
just saying that that's already been
taken into account um with the variable
one you know the develop variable that
i've defined here um in my kappa so i've
just called it zero for now
now one thing that you need to
understand with the hester model is that
you can get negative volatility if this
condition is not satisfied if two times
kappa times theta is is not greater than
sigma
squared then you're going to have issues
but here i've convinced myself that this
condition holds so i'm not worried even
if i discretize
now the bredon litzenberger formula here
let's determine the risk neutral
probability distribution function so as
we said before it's that discounted
factor
so here remember that we had um that our
second order um derivative was equal to
the discount factor uh times by the pdf
i've just taken that discount factor and
now we've got the forward factor
multiplied by this second order
derivative now in order to approximate
that derivative we're going to use
finite difference approximation so in
actuality what that looks like is we're
going to uh we're going to get our call
prices
for different strikes and then we're
going to make sure that these strikes
have an even difference in between them
and we're going to use this formula
that are centered around a particular
strike to be able to calculate our risk
neutral distribution for that particular
strike at that time to maturity
we're just going to be defining a 2d
pdf here for a particular time to
maturity now for actually calculating um
option prices under the hester model
what we've got is an analytical solution
and that is in terms of the
characteristic equation and hester model
that we have here please look at a
previous video that i've got linked up
on the screen right now where we've
actually taken you through how to
calculate this from the characteristic
function so essentially it's a
two-parter here i need to be calculating
complex integrals on this domain from 0
to infinity
of this characteristic function
now here i've defined what that
characteristic function is and then i
need to compute that complex integration
and the way that i'm doing that is
through rectangular integration so here
i step through
my domain size from zero to infinity but
you don't need to go that far for option
pricing i've just gone to 100 here and
we're going to take 650 segments now
it's really important
because
with our complex integration here
the step size that you choose will
really impact especially for out of the
money
options will really impact your
precision of calculation and the reason
is that python has this terrible
round-off issue
because it stores things in terms of
binary variables it's decimals in terms
of binary variables we will talk about
that later and why the quant lib that's
implemented in c is much more effective
at completing this numerical integration
anyway
we can implement this uh
this equation and we're going to take
the real component of the option price
as we've defined in the formula
up here so we have an analytical
solution semi-analytical solution we
still need to compute this
this numerically across this using
rectangular integration
so for a whole bunch of strikes i'm
going to take 60 through to 180 with a
step of one i'm going to calculate my
option prices of the heston price using
rectangular integration i've defined all
my variables as above so once we've
calculated these
option prices under the hester model
then we're going to use second order
finite difference approximation
to actually calculate the risk neutral
distribution and the curvature
so here
you'll note that we have this risk
neutral distribution as that forward
factor times by a second order finite
difference approximation so let's
actually just place that within a data
frame our strike in our option prices
that we have above and then we're going
to use the shift function to get the
strike price above and the strike price
below
so here we've got minus two of the
current uh call option prices so two
times that that price here then we've
got plus uh the next strike above so we
just use the shift by one function in
pandas data frame
and we're going to add the shift price
minus one so the strike below then we're
going to divide that whole summation
through
by the step size squared that we took in
the step size of course with just one
strike
so we did that by definition when we
defined and calculated our option
prices so let's plot what that looks
like
and what that curvature looks like
so here we have our heston
stochastic volatility calculated option
prices and that's in the blue and then
here we've got our curvature
on the y-axis which is really the
density function now here i haven't
taken the forward factor
so it's approximately the pdf here and
we'll do that in the next step but see
here we've got some issues because
on the left hand side you can see here
how the curvature actually dips below
zero so we have a density that's below
zero so obviously that doesn't hold and
therefore
this is just impactful by the roundoff
errors as you get out of the money
the calculation with our rectangular
integration function does not do so well
so let's compare this with the quant lib
hester model so here we've taken a lot
of this code from quant stack exchange
on this question here which is computing
the probability density function of the
hester model go figure
i haven't used quant lib
a lot but obviously i think it would be
good going forward to actually benchmark
a lot of the models that we're
implementing here in python with the
quant lib library
so
here you have to define your date ranges
of the product that you're actually
valuing
setting up your discount curve and
you've got a flat curve and then a yield
curve
then you need to have a heston model so
you define your heston process with all
the factors that we have
identified above so your spot price and
then your initial volatility kappa theta
sigma and rho
and then you create the model from the
process
you have this heston handle
model handle
class and then that goes into creating
your heston black vole surface now from
that we can use the dot black foal
function
for a particular time to maturity and a
particular strike k
so once we've got our voles we can then
use that to calculate
the correct heston pricing method given
the heston analytical engine so once
we've got the heston prices we just
append that
as the discounted expectation of those
prices and then we can add that into our
pandas data frame
so let's compare our rectangular
integration with our quant library so
here you can see we're actually just
calculating that exact same graph as
before we have call prices in blue
on the main axis and then on the y
second y axis here we've got that
density
and the difference is you can see that
the density has not dropped below zero
which is ideal for a probability density
function so
obviously we're going to go with this
one now what are the differences and why
so to look at the differences we can
first look at the mse we can look at the
mean of the difference of the option
prices from our rectangular integration
to the quant lib library
mse is very small across all these
strikes 0.07 and you can see
only small differences here
between
at all these strikes
now it does it does get larger
especially when you get out of the money
further and further and the reason for
that is
we have a large
now the main reason for the difference
is because of a result of the complex
integration over really small increments
now python has big issues with round off
errors at small values approximated
because of the binary float point
numbers because
python actually approximates these
decimal
values by binary float point numbers we
get rounding errors and i've put two
links there
that you can investigate to see why that
is the fact quantlib is obviously more
effective at this it's actually been
implemented in c and
handles decimal points a different way
within their calculation so they've got
a slightly better numerical integration
scheme than our
year 12 rectangular integration i would
love to hear your solutions for python
in how we can actually get this
numerical integration um a little bit
better and then more precise maybe
taking different step size functions and
making that variable for different
strikes i would love to hear your
suggestions in the comment section below
how can i improve my
rectangular integration function
so now we've got we've got a discretize
approximate pdf so i want to take
those prices
that curvature and i'm going to multiply
by our forward factor now
so i've got our forward factor
multiplied by the curvature
array and what i want to do is i want to
use psi pi interpolate
and i'm going to interpolate between the
strikes so given a strike i want to be
able to interpolate our discrete
curvature function so i want a pdf
given the strike i'm going to get back
the curvature
so
i'm going to use two different types of
pdfs
so i'm going to use two different types
of interpolation i'm going to use linear
and cubic and we're going to look at the
difference between the two now really
important here
sci pi is only going to be able to then
compute the strikes so once we've
actually created this
interpolation method we can only
actually calculate on between the
interval of the data that we've given it
so we gave it uh
strikes between 60 and 180 um so we can
only
calculate uh strikes between those so
i've gotten from 61 to 179
and here we've got the
pdf using the cubic and then pdf using
the linear function
so as you can see our disk our forward
multiplied by the curvature has given
these really nice pdfs
of which cubic and linear i'm not seeing
much of a difference perhaps it would
have made a difference if we took larger
step sizes in our strikes
and of course you might be limited if
you're using market data to imply this
directly but here i'm pretty comfortable
with the linear interpolation
that we've got here
so how can i get the cumulative
distribution function of this wrist
neutral density function well
essentially what i'm going to do
is i'm going to take the cumulative sum
of the pdf so
i've got the pdf linear of all the
strikes i'm taking the cumulative sum of
the pdf which is
in fact the cdf but that's the discrete
cdf
for each particular strike and again i'm
just going to use a linear
function
using scipy interpolate interpo
one dimensional so here we've got our
cdf
and now i'm going to plot across all
those strikes and we're going to look at
what that looks like
so here we've got our cdf of our risk
neutral distribution at a particular
time to maturity so tau and you can plug
in a k and you get the probability back
so how do we actually use the risk
neutral pdfs to price complex
derivatives so remember here that this
wrist neutral density function is
defined at a particular time to maturity
time to expiry tau
at this point
it's extremely model independent
we have a risk neutral density function
um at a particular uh time to maturity
that has either taken in market prices
or taken in a particular model like
we've used the hester model
and now we can use that risk neutral
density density function with those
particular parameters etc all embedded
within this pdf what do i mean by that
well i'll show you here we've got a
generic pricing formula for just a call
and a put and this is in terms of k and
tau
so
now i can just to complete
this numerical integration of this pdf
our risk neutral pdf for a particular
tau
of
my call payoff which is just st minus k
between k to infinity or for a put it's
uh the interval minus infinity to k of k
minus st
now i'm going to do both of those so
here we've got our we're defining our
integrand which is just in terms of x so
our us our
stock price and then we've got an
argument k
so here we're returning uh our stock
price minus k times by our wrist neutral
pdf now we've got our integrand of
output which is just the opposite we've
got k minus x
now our integral for the call is defined
on the interval from k to infinity but
of course we can't go to infinity our
maximum cdf that we can calculate
because of our interpolation is uh to
180 so here i've just gone 178
and then of course then we've got our
integrand between k and one seven eight
i've limited it to one thousand and then
i've got my argument of k being fed into
that integrand function
i'm then going to compute for f for each
k in our strikes and the put using the
same integrand but our interval is going
to be from minus infinity again our
lowest defined range which is
essentially 0
as we can see from our
cdf i've got 61
and then i'm going to k so here now i've
got the discount factor multiplied by
our integral and then i've done the same
for the put
so we can append those values and then
we can display them in a pandas data
frame
and here i'm just showing you how we've
been able to price both
puts and calls
within
for different strikes as easily as that
and if it was really high dimensions we
had high time steps it takes high
complexity to be able to calculate this
whether it's model dependent um the
actually pricing things off the wrist
neutral density functions is very very
efficient so i would encourage you to go
out and try and derive wrist neutral
density functions for whatever you're
interested in in one of the next videos
we're going to look at how we can
actually take market prices and do model
independent risk neutral density
functions from the market implied prices
so thank you very much for listening
until next time youtube see you later